Guide to the Franz Sigel Papers 1806-1930 MS 565
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
- Series VII: Sigel Family Papers, 1806-1915, undated (Box 7)
  Within this series there are three subseries. The documents contained within this series are in both English and German, with the bulk of German in the first two subseries. There are letters, telegrams, and some official documents.
  - Subseries A: Moritz Sigel Papers, 1806-1859 (Box 7)
    Moritz Sigel was Franz Sigel’s father. Like Sigel, Moritz took part in the 1848 revolution and had to leave Germany. He managed to escape when the revolution failed and, like his son, went to the United States and settled in New York City. However, just before the outbreak of the American Civil War, Moritz petitioned the Prussians for a pardon and was able to return to Germany in 1859. All of the documents in this subseries are written in German. There appear to be a number of official documents with seals and a diploma. The majority are handwritten documents that appear to be letters and notes.
    - Moritz Sigel Papers, 1806-1842 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Moritz Sigel Papers, 1842-1842 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Moritz Sigel Papers, 1851-1859 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Subseries B: Elise Sigel Papers, 1861-1910, undated (Box 7)
    This subseries which begins during the American Civil War years and ends in the early twentieth century consists of letters and telegrams. The bulk is letters, and those letters are mostly written in German. There are some notable exceptions when the correspondence is in English. Those instances are typically condolence letters or telegrams after Sigel died in 1902.
    - Correspondence, 1861-1862 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1863-1865 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1866-1901 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1902-1910, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Subseries C: Other Family Papers, 1900-1915 (Box 7)
    Within this subseries are Franz Sigel Jr.’s papers and other family correspondence. Franz Sigel Jr.’s papers consist mainly of telegrams telling of his father’s deteriorating health and then ones conveying condolences. There is also a letter from the Gen. Franz Sigel Monument Committee. The other family correspondence contains only a few documents which are written in German.
    - Franz Sigel Jr. Papers, 1902-1905 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Family Correspondence, 1900-1915 (Box 7, Folder 16)